<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog.atom"/>
  <title>Rocky Mountain Dog Training - The Dog Blog</title>
  <updated>2021-06-10T10:53:32-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Rocky Mountain Dog Training</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/the-new-era-of-dog-training</id>
    <published>2021-06-10T10:53:32-06:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-12T17:07:37-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/the-new-era-of-dog-training"/>
    <title>Change Is Coming: The New Era of Dog Training </title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p data-pm-slice="1 1 []">The state of dog training, with all the advancements in the field still has an element missing that is creating welfare implications and unattainable expectations for our dogs and ourselves. How did we get here? Let's explore.</p><p><a class="read-more" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/the-new-era-of-dog-training">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p data-pm-slice="1 1 []">Over the weekend, I was listening to a live chat with two great minds in our field. Generally speaking, the topic was the state of dog training and how with all the advancements in our field, there's still an element missing that is creating welfare implications and unattainable expectations for our dogs and ourselves. </p>
<p>We're getting inquiries for more behavior cases than ever, to the point that there are not enough trainers to go around. How did we get here?</p>
<p><strong>Problem #1: Inappropriate Breed Selection</strong></p>
<p><strong><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/AdobeStock_329795358.jpg?v=1623344042" alt=""></strong></p>
<p>When selecting pet dogs to add to the family, we rarely think to ourselves:</p>
<p><em>"This breed is a bad-ass vermin-hunting machine! There are lots of bunnies in our neighborhood that we're going to encounter. This breed is likely to lunge at them on our walks. Am I prepared for this?"</em> </p>
<p>Or, <em>"This breed was developed for driving cattle over long stretches of terrain and is purposefully bred to herd by biting. Plus they have outstanding stamina. How is that going to play out when my kids have their friends over and they're running around in the yard?" </em></p>
<p>Instead, we see a cute puppy and consumerism kicks in. "Must have that puppy!" Marketing has tricked us into believing that all dogs are created equal and if there's ever a problem, surely it's the dog. We rarely look to the environment we've plopped them into and the expectations we now have for them. </p>
<p>When they hit adolescence, and one is going apeshit on leash walks every time he sees a small critter -- because he needs to express the behavior he was born to do -- and the other is biting the kid's ankles when they're playing -- because she too is expressing the behavior she was born to do -- we think, "This dog's broken and needs to be fixed." This brings about problem 2.</p>
<p><strong>Problem #2: The Fix-It Mentality</strong></p>
<p>If the general consensus is, "My dog is broken," then surely we can fix this, right? Marketing kicks in yet again. Marketing tells you that Yes! Everything is fixable!</p>
<p><em>But... What if they're not actually broken?</em> </p>
<p>These dogs are doing exactly what they and many generations prior were selectively bred for. One of the purposes of selective breeding is to exaggerate certain behavior tendencies to a highly specialized degree to serve a functional purpose. Thus, they are not actually broken. </p>
<p>Our job as ethical trainers is rarely just about the dog. Hands down, the most difficult aspect of the job is creating realistic expectations for the families who fell under the spell of an adorable puppy that might not be the best fit for their household, and now have to modify their own habits and the dog's surrounding environment in order to bring about reasonable resolution. </p>
<p>It can be a hard sell, but we have an obligation to be honest, accurate and ethical in our approach. At least we should strive for this. </p>
<p><strong>Problem #3: Confirmation Bias </strong></p>
<p>The whole purpose of marketing is to make the sale. Marketing tells you exactly what you want to hear. Marketing also exploits confirmation bias. Tell me, consumer, which offer would you go with? </p>
<p><u>Offer 1:</u> <em>"Yes the dog is broken. I will fix post haste!"</em></p>
<p><u>Offer 2:</u> <em>"He's actually a completely normal terrier, but if we change his environment and our behavior a bit, we can bring this to a manageable level over time."</em></p>
<p>We are primed to go with the allure of offer #1 because it is counter-intuitive to consider the other. Confirmation bias says, "don't spend your energy doing pesky things like thinking about this, this person already agrees with your assessment and just like you saw on TV the results will be practically instantaneous!" Unfortunately, even those with highly developed critical thinking skills can fall prey to this at times. It's safe to say that at this point we all know the dangers of confirmation bias run amok, and let me tell you, it's a widespread issue in the training world too. </p>
<p>But here's the thing: Dogs aren't products. Dogs are companions. They are captive animals fully dependent on us as their caregivers and guardians. They have emotions, they have needs and we are morally obligated to treat them with kindness, understanding, and as the family members that they are. </p>
<p>By heading into training with the mentality that the dog is broken -- an incorrect assessment -- it allows for all kinds of horrific acts to be bestowed upon the dog in the name of fixing it. So what are we fixing if the dog isn't actually broken?  </p>
<p>On the one side of the training world, we have an approach involving suppression of behavior. Punish it out. This approach is one dimensional and does not account for the dog's experience. By leaving the dog with no outlet for expression, the dog tries another approach. That behavior is in turn shut down. Eventually we shut down so many expressions of behavior that the dog is boxed into a corner. They aren't allowed to be a dog. Punishment as a standalone option is not ethical. The initial behavior is now long gone but at what cost? What is their quality of life? </p>
<p>We don't have to look far for relatable examples. Remember the initial phase of the pandemic when we were on a full lock-down? Even though it was only a couple months in that phase, and even though many of our sacrifices were relatively small, people lost their minds. Then we went into partial restrictions for another year. Even the most introverted introvert started to struggle. Now imagine 12 years of that first phase. Except in your house, maybe you can't even talk. You also can't creatively entertain yourself because it's annoying or messy to your housemates. There's no TV, books aren't allowed, and certainly no hobbies. When you do go out, you're not allowed to explore your surroundings, because exploring is bad!  Would your mental health suffer? Of course! So why in god's name are we doing this to our dogs? </p>
<p>Like all us sentient beings, dogs should be looked at thoughtfully, factoring in their breed specialties, the household environment and all the members of that household during the selection process. Like introverts and extroverts in our own kind, some dogs are better suited for certain environments than others and if the environment is too restrictive, all will suffer. </p>
<p>We have moved to a mentality that dogs are like trinkets that we take out when we want and shelve them when we don't. Couple that with a belief that all dogs are the same off the shelf and when one becomes problematic, it's broken and we need to fix it. It's a recipe for disaster. </p>
<p>On the other side of the training spectrum we have modern dog trainers. Modern dog trainers strive to protect the dogs under their charge from punitive corrections that simply shut down behaviors and instead look to treat the emotion the dog is feeling because the emotion is causing the symptom and when treated, the &lt;insert observable behavior problem&gt; goes away. </p>
<p>Even in modern group classes with behaviorally healthy dogs, the objective is still to teach the dog to do this skill when I say. This falls short. </p>
<p>Society still believes in placing dogs in a subservient role.  As such, if you're trying to sell services, you are at the mercy of societal expectations. </p>
<p>While we do need to teach functional behaviors to be able to keep dogs and our communities safe, there is much more to these relationships that gets missed by focusing solely on this approach. Many of the behaviors families think they want out of a class aren't all that useful for today's pet dogs. This, dear reader, causes loads of heartburn for most of us trainers. We feel stuck.  </p>
<p>We're keenly aware of societal expectations, and that we need to shift a bit, but our livelihood is very much tied to meeting these expectations. If you ask almost any modern dog trainer, they'll describe the hours they've spent agonizing over this, because most of us already know there's more to a successful relationship than the one-sided approach that is expected in today's classes. We know that dogs are still drawing the short straw even though we've moved away from physically hurting them in the name of training. </p>
<p>For me, I have my ideal curriculum all laid out in my head. It looks at the entire life of a pet dog and the situations they're most likely to experience stress, and seeks to protect them from that. There are still behaviors taught that help us to direct them appropriately and keep safety at the forefront, but they are significantly pared down from what our current curriculum offers. In place of the less useful behaviors, we would focus on breed-specific needs and on their need to feel safe in situations that are inherently difficult for them. This sounds so hippy-dippy, but the reality is that happy dogs, dogs whose needs are met and who are shielded from fear don't generally exhibit loads of behavior problems. Are there exceptions? Of course. But by and large this approach is a win for both the dogs and the families.  </p>
<p><strong>Reality, Though</strong></p>
<p>Sadly, my dream curriculum would absolutely bomb as an offering on my website in today's marketplace. We as a society haven't caught up to this way of thinking, but change is coming and my students are already seeing bits of this trickle in and the reception has been positive. </p>
<p><strong>Evolution of the Field</strong></p>
<p>With the sky-high numbers of behavioral challenges we're seeing, practitioners recognize that the one-sided approach to training is failing dogs. The new era of dog training seeks to meet the dog in the middle. We give a little, they give a little, everyone is happier for it. It looks at the individual breed characteristics both in selection for the household and it helps to create a lifestyle under which both the humans AND the dog can thrive. </p>
<p>In the talk that inspired this writing, they discussed a simple but incredibly powerful question. A question that allows us to shift our mindset when engaging with our dogs. I ask that when interacting with your own dog, you start to ask this question as part of your everyday engagements. It will enable you to become part of the movement to increase their welfare. </p>
<p><strong>"What is my dog experiencing right now?"</strong> </p>
<p>By asking this question, we're taking time to understand their experience, and it shifts the dynamic from control to support and understanding. </p>
<p>It's what we want in life, right? Why would our dogs be any different? </p>
<p>What is my dog experiencing right now? It's time to start asking this question and shift our thinking on how we relate to our dogs. </p>
<p><em>Thank you so much to Andrew Hale - Dog Centred Care  and Kim Brophy - The Dog Door for this inspirational talk that led to this writing. I look forward to exploring this concept further and integrating more of this into our programs. For more information on selecting the right breed for your household, check out this wonderful book, <a href="https://tinyurl.com/yruwap3j" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Meet Your Dog - by Kim Brophy.</a></em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/the-childhood-memory-i-wish-i-could-forget</id>
    <published>2020-08-10T08:19:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-08-10T14:06:01-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/the-childhood-memory-i-wish-i-could-forget"/>
    <title>The Childhood Memory I Wish I Could Forget</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>When we were kids, we had a beautiful, gentle dog named Spits. He was our first dog having only had cats prior. Spits was a really good-natured, goofy boy. Leggy. He galloped when he ran. He smiled all the time. He had a really long tongue. My sister and I adored this dog. When I'd get home from school, from outings, from wherever, I always remember that the first thing I would do was find him and say hello and give him a pat. He'd lean his head into me, looking at me with that big smile and tongue hanging to the side.</p>
<p>On one particular day I'd been out with my grandparents. I remember we'd gone to the mall in Ventura. When I got home, my sister was sitting on the couch with an ice cube, and my dog was nowhere to be found. I finally asked where he was and my mom told me he'd bitten my sister and that he's not coming home. My sister then broke into hysterical crying and said she thought he was purring but then he bit her face.</p>
<p>I will never forget my sister's sobs, tears and melting ice pooling at her chin. We are both very sensitive and this was felt to the core.</p>
<p>I was beside myself. In fact I don't know that I'd ever been so distressed in my early life. "I will never see my dog again? I want to see him. Let me at least say goodbye. Where is he? How could this happen? You thought he was purring?!" Thinking about it now, it still really hurts and the tears are rolling as I type. We were young, maybe 6 max. But it's seared into my memory, that awful day. I haven't thought about it in many years. Like a lot of painful experiences, you sometimes stuff them down. Try to forget.</p>
<p>A couple days ago, my sister called me to talk about it. She'd seen something online that triggered her memory of it and she was again beside herself crying because all these years she's carried that weight around. Feeling responsible. Seared into her memory too. She says she remembers it vividly like it was yesterday. We're in our forties. This was at least 35 years ago. She still felt responsible. She still worried about his fate. She still carries the guilt.</p>
<p>We talked about the experience from her perspective, something we've never done before. A child's view. On the surface, it was clear what had happened. She was laying on him, petting him, and looking into his eyes. He was growling for a long time. She said at least a minute and a half. She continued engaging with him, and he snapped at her, bit her superficially on the lip and ran away. But let's look at this in finer detail.</p>
<p>As children, we'd grown up with cats. Cats purr. For a young child, it's not a big leap to assume the growling he was doing was purring given her experience with pets being primarily cats and that's precisely what she thought. She thought he was purring. She was certain he was enjoying the interaction and continued with it because she loved him. My sister and I are both animal lovers to the core. We both work in the pet industry. We both advocate heavily for them and that advocacy was certainly in part shaped by this one incident.</p>
<p>Because Spits was such a good boy, he tried his hardest to tell her in a peaceful way that he wanted space but she couldn't understand. He tried vocalizations by way of growling for a long time. Those vocalizations expressed his feelings in a peaceful way. This is their language. When, after an eternity in his mind he couldn't get relief, he finally escalated to a bite which was superficial in nature. In fact, it was so inhibited, the ice she'd had on her lip did more damage than the bite itself when it got stuck to her lip as she cried.</p>
<p>Let's be real. He could have crushed her skull. Stop thinking dogs aren't capable of this, they most certainly are. Instead of using force, he used his voice. What a good boy. When that didn't work, he used a gentle nip and ran off. What a good boy. Do I sound crazy? Calling a biting a dog a good boy? I'm not. He was gentle in all of the interactions. He didn't have to be. He was certainly capable of much worse. He chose to be gentle. He was a good boy. It wasn't good enough I guess because he was gone and we were distraught.</p>
<p>Listen, I've had worse injuries scraping my arms on dog crates while moving them around. He lost everything for this. What a tragedy. Can we stop acting like dogs are demons for this? In his case, he just needed an advocate and they both needed supervision. Sure there are times where dogs and kids shouldn't be in the same household. This wasn't one of them.</p>
<p>I asked her where our parents were. They were in the kitchen. She was unsupervised. I asked where did they take him? She doesn't know. "Away." Neither of us know his fate for certain but given how quickly he was gone, the shelter is most likely. If he was taken to the shelter, it's doubtful he made it out alive. He was a wonderful dog, he did everything right, but dogs with bite histories, no matter how un-at-fault and un-damaging the bite,  cannot from a liability perspective be re-homed. Honestly, I don't know that I can handle the truth of what happened to him. I don't want to know.</p>
<p>At the time I blamed my sister about the loss of my dog. I was heartbroken. I thought it was her fault. I was young too (we're twins) and so my thinking was simplistic. But it was not her fault. It was not Spits's fault either. He was a good dog.</p>
<p>When those in a position of responsibility take good nature for granted, bad things can and do happen. There were no signs prior to this day that this would ever occur. None. But we don't ever truly know what a dog is going through in the moment. He may have been in pain. Maybe arthritis was kicking in. Maybe her being on his body was uncomfortable, it doesn't matter. He was clear that he was not ok. And it fell on the deaf ears of an innocent child. Parents were not present to interpret and to keep them both safe. But my parents while responsible are not abnormal. Parents the world over get busy, get comfortable, lose sight of risk. They were complacent.</p>
<p>Early in my career I often commented on YouTube videos, posts and pictures of interactions either going horribly wrong or where the distressed dog seemed to amuse the masses. I tried with all I could muster to educate. It never did a damn bit of good. I found myself being ridiculed. I was called the fun police a lot, told to lighten up. Told that "they're fine, nothing happened." "It's cute." "You're a Debbie downer." ad nauseum. But in those videos and pictures, I was seeing dogs in distress, hearing dogs growling, and watching parents giggle away while shooting video of their precious baby in harm's way, and ignoring the distress the dog was already under. I was reading in comments how funny all this was. For my own sanity, I finally just started blocking everything of this nature and everyone who thought it was funny. A practice I mostly adhere to even now. Dogs in distress and children in harm's way is not funny. You're being irresponsible.</p>
<p>In my business, I doubled down on body language education. Educating before it becomes a problem often prevents people from normalizing warning signals. They can't unsee it. They now know and are aware and instead of getting complacent recognize it as a problem to seek relief for. It's all about prevention. I knew that I hated seeing all this stuff, advocated very hard for the dog and child, and was and still am really hardcore about the importance of understanding body language. I didn't recognize why until yesterday, as my sister and I talked, that I was so driven on this topic. It was too painful to think about.</p>
<p>Parents, I'm sharing this story to let you know from yet another angle the importance of supervision. Maybe this story will stick. The dog isn't at fault. The child is not at fault. You really have to stay diligent. It is your responsibility to keep them safe. Dogs and young children are not equipped to do this on their own. One moment can change everything.</p>
<p>35 years! That's how long my sister has been feeling the guilt of this. 35 years! A wonderful childhood companion most likely paid with his life for a completely preventable event.</p>
<p>Distress is not funny. You're the parent, the guardian, the caregiver. Whatever label you'd like. This is your job. This shouldn't have happened. Thousands of times a year there are horrible incidents with dogs and kids that shouldn't have happened. That have long lasting psychological impacts on the child and result in death of the dog. There are full websites dedicated to blaming dogs.  You know who is never held responsible? The parents. It's sickening. If I sound bitter, it's because I am. I'm hurt. My sister and I shouldn't be carrying around this pain. Do you want your child living with that trauma? It hurts my heart that I never got to say goodbye. It hurts that my sister is crying about this over 3 decades later. It hurts my heart that my dog lost all he knew, and probably his life.</p>
<p>So please, let's not participate in normalizing distress in dogs. Let's do work on our roles in prevention, and please for the love of all things holy, let's stop good dogs from dying at the hands of our poor decisions.</p>
<p>My sister and I talked for a long time about that day. I apologized profusely for giving her grief about it as kids, we lamented about Spits, and we're still, 35+ years later, grieving his loss. Thank you Charlotte for giving me permission to share this story. Our hope is that it prevents someone else from living it.</p>
<p>To Spits, you loved us and we loved you and I'm so sorry. You were a very good boy. To my sister, it's not your fault. It was never your fault. I'm so sorry for ever thinking it was. To parents everywhere, please take this to heart. You are responsible for keeping them safe.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/crating-benefits-everyone</id>
    <published>2020-07-31T10:49:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-07-31T11:32:47-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/crating-benefits-everyone"/>
    <title>Crating Benefits Everyone</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Our <strong><a href="/pages/puppy-day-school">Puppy Day School</a></strong> program is built for young bodies to learn, grow and fulfill their potential. One aspect we're both asked about a lot and can present a challenge in this setting is crating and downtime. I'll address both separately.</p>
<p>When they are with us from 7:30am - 1:00pm give a little on either side for pick up and drop off, why would we rest them? Well, overly tired puppies are not productive puppies, they can and do make less desirable choices and learning retention isn't nearly as strong. Overly tired puppies can be easily overwhelmed. The opposite of what our goals are here. They have multiple structured activities daily, each focused on different aspects of development. As a baby, could you run a marathon? Probably not. They can't either, but they will try! We as their caregivers during their time with us are focused on optimizing their time with us, and with that, we need to be sure we don't overwork them. During transitions and potty breaks, we address this by providing them with short bouts of rest time in their crates. If you've ever been with an overly tired puppy, even for a few minutes, you know exactly why this rest is vital. We always describe it as the kid who was at the zoo an hour too long and is now losing their mind over nothing identifiable. Not good. Crating comfortably amongst other dogs and in places outside the home is also an incredibly valuable skill set if they're ever to dabble in the dog sports world, or even travel with you.</p>
<p><strong>So what happens when a puppy has never been exposed to a crate or only sleeps overnight in one? A couple things are likely to occur: </strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Fear of Missing Out (FOMO)</li>
<li>Anxiety of Being Alone or Confined</li>
</ol>
<p><em>FOMO</em> typically presents as a dog who overnights well in their crate because nothing is going on so there is nothing to miss out on, but when the household is active, the puppy screams if confined. If we are cycling dogs in <strong><a href="/pages/puppy-day-school">Puppy Day School</a></strong>, this frustration of not being out while others are impacts their ability to rest. This causes serious frustration for the dog. Frustration = stress, and this type of stress is not good for a puppy.</p>
<p><em>Fear of Being Alone.</em> This has historically been infrequent, but as we're in the midst of a pandemic, everyone is home, and so nowadays we're seeing multiple puppies weekly who are facing this. This can quickly turn into full blown anxiety, and that is a very real, very serious problem that has long term detrimental effects on quality of life. Dogs experiencing this are suffering. It's not something to take lightly or assume they'll grow out of. They don't.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/20200716_210919_grande.jpg?v=1596214401" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>So how do these things impact their <strong><a href="/pages/puppy-day-school">Puppy Day School</a></strong> programs? Stress is cumulative. If they are unable to rest, worked into a state of stress frequently, it impacts everything. Their learning, their ability to make good choices in play, their moods, their interest in training and their perception of the world. If this doesn't sound right, think of you own behavior. Have you ever dealt with low or high grade stress throughout the day, then something seemingly minor (like having to decide what's for dinner) send you over the top? That's cumulative stress.</p>
<p>How extensively does it impact the program? It impacts it a lot. Have you ever tried to sleep next to someone who snores loudly? It sucks. Ask my partner. But that's nothing. Imagine trying to sleep next to someone screaming nonstop, or every few seconds. When puppies come into the program without this skill, it impacts all their puppy classmates. They can't get rest either. If one of those puppies struggles with sound sensitivity, it can be downright scary for them.</p>
<p>It impacts us trainers too. When you know without question that a dog is struggling, you go through the day holding that stress with you too, and there are decisions that take place, sometimes decisions the families don't want to hear but that are right for the dog. Ethical. our mantra is do no harm.</p>
<p>We need to keep very close tabs on dogs that struggle with this. These dogs desperately need socialization. Their worlds are smaller than ever right now with the pandemic. They also need down time for us to optimize their progression through the programs. It's also against our ethics to place them in harm's way. This presents us with a conundrum. Is it better to sacrifice some stress for socialization? How stressed is this puppy in their down time? Is it impacting others? Is it impacting their progress? The problem with all of this is that it requires a sacrifice either in the dog feeling crate stress or by removing them from the program and missing out on socialization. These decisions can become very complex factoring a number of attributes. All of this takes time away from what our program is built for - <a href="/products/puppy-socialization"><strong>Socialization</strong></a> and in the case of <a href="/products/puppy-day-school"><strong>Ultimate Puppy Clients</strong></a> - Training.</p>
<p>So why don't we work on crating as part of the program? We actually do, but our role is primarily maintenance of skills that were started in the home. This week is what has spurred me to write about this because this week has been very taxing for the struggling dogs and for my team. This week, we have several dogs who do not have crating skills who started the program. It's been extremely loud. Restful it is not. I worry about my neighboring businesses getting upset too.</p>
<p>So what do we do when this happens? During playgroup when we have the ability, and we have dogs struggling, we will work in shifts where 3 will run playgroup with (for instance) the smalls, and another trainer will work on happy crating with the bigs, walking up and down the aisle and feeding the puppies who are crated treat by treat, working to build a positive association. Sometimes though, playgroup requires all trainers to be present, and so to remove one to work on crating isn't always possible. This then leads to dogs who are not resting during their breaks. And the cycle continues, where we aren't able to optimize their programs because we don't have all pieces in play.</p>
<p>Why not hire another trainer to work specifically on crate training? Well, sticker shock. Our program is paid in a lump sum. The cost being $1900 for Ultimate Puppies for 4 weeks of half-days. In reality, that is actually approximately $23 per hour which is a screaming deal for professional training that you just need to maintain at home, (don't forget there are 2 private sessions included in the Ultimate package if you think my math is off) and the program comes with weekly instructional videos and material so you can keep up to speed on what we're doing, and start building a training relationship with your puppy on the skills they've learned here at home. A freaking steal! But if we raise rates higher to bring in more help, it causes more sticker shock. If we hired another trainer without raising rates we would go into the negative in a serious hurry. We need to keep things economical or this wonderful program becomes out of reach financially for puppies who really need it. </p>
<p>If we just take on more dogs, we don't get to spend as much time with each, and they would then spend a ton of time in those darn crates, so it's a fine line. Places that don't cap numbers cap the amount of time spent with each dog. If you want to pay all that for mostly daytime boarding and a little training and socialization, that's fine, but that's not our program. We have very high standards for our programs and for our trainers, and part of that is optimizing their programs, not getting greedy, and serving each individual dog's needs.</p>
<p>And that's where our clients come in. This crating thing. We really need your help prior to dogs attending the program in getting them acclimated to their crates. These short bouts of rest are important for the dog's overall well-being, allow us to focus on the job you hired us to do (training and socialization) and we can perform to the best of our abilities under these contexts. We can help your dog meet their full potential. Doesn't that sound way better than meeting some of their potential?</p>
<p>So parents, you've gotta set aside time for this. No, crate training isn't super fun or glamorous, but it is important for your puppy and it will help us make the most of your investment. Because dogs that cannot comfortably crate take away the quality of the program for themselves and other puppy clients, we have to make hard choices about their ability to stay in or be released from the program, so please do your part. Get them going on daytime crating skills, get them comfortable in there for short bouts, and we will all win! You will have a crate training plan and instructions sent to you prior to attending to guide you on this.</p>
<p>And you know what? That skill will definitely come in handy in the future for travel, camping, dog sports, surgeries, etc. Your puppy is worth it!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dogs-and-plants-and-behavior</id>
    <published>2020-06-30T12:01:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-30T13:01:03-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dogs-and-plants-and-behavior"/>
    <title>Dogs and Plants and Behavior</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>In January, my grandparents removed the 50 year old fig tree from their yard. The tree carried a lot of sentimental value as I'd grown up enjoying its fruits and beauty, sharing it with friends, climbing it, and enjoying its shade. I decided to take some cuttings home from California because I couldn't handle the thought of that being the end of it. This meant taking small branches, giving them a home with lots of light, humidity, warmth, soil and water. It was winter. They were coming from California. Figs are not known to fare well in Colorado's climate, definitely not our cold. I also live in an older home with small windows and not nearly as much light as they'd need. I still wanted to give it my best shot.</span></p>
<p><span>After much research, I bought some root starter, dipped them all and put them into a mulch mix designed for starting tree cuttings. I purchased artificial light and big plastic sheets to hold in the moisture for them. I watered them and once I saw they were capable of sprouting leaves, I stopped watering them all together. Predictably, they died. I was so mad at my plants. I kept thinking, "They KNOW how to grow..."</span><br><span>No, actually, they lived in the back bathroom until April and are currently thriving by our back sliding glass door. </span></p>
<p><span>When I finally transplanted them, it was long overdue because the garden stores were closed (pandemic) so getting soil was a challenge. They were looking rough. I stuck with it and I'm happy to report that they are now beautiful, healthy plants. New growth has even surfaced through the soil. In Colorado. In a dark house with few sun-facing windows.</span></p>
<p><strong>I was admiring them this morning and thinking of the parallels between plants and dogs.</strong></p>
<p class="medium-up--one-half" style="margin: 0 auto;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/104220664_10158502251815421_2309863472845222156_o.jpg?v=1593543572"></p>
<p><span>I chose a plant I loved and put it into an environment it is ill-fitted for. I had to work really hard for my fig trees to thrive here. I had to constantly revise my behavior to get them through. If they'd been in their intended environment, it would have been much easier for them and for me.</span></p>
<p><span>Selecting dogs on environmental fit is important too. But if you just love field labs, and are fairly sedentary, you're going to have to work much harder for them to flourish. If you love working breeds, you'll need to provide them with high volumes of mentally stimulating activities and decent amounts of exercise - more than an average energy dog might require. If you opt for a cattle dog, know that they've been intentionally bred to herd by biting, and so if you've got kids in the house, you're going to have to work extra EXTRA hard to mitigate this, and likely not just in training, in management of the environment too.</span></p>
<p><span>My figs in Colorado are the cattle dogs of the plant world. This particular variety grows into a big tree, but here, it won't be able to survive outside, and my house just isn't big enough to accommodate a full sized tree. I'm likely going to have to bonsai it. Lots more work. I'm going to have to manage their environment closely.</span><br><span>Like my figs, some dogs will take a lot of extra work if the environment isn't really what they're meant for, but if you're willing to put in the time and effort, they can absolutely thrive. When their needs are met, they flourish.</span></p>
<p><span>But all dogs are like plants and their skills need maintenance care that happens for life. There is a misconception that once a dog is trained, that's it! They know it. Imagine me being like, "There, you've learned how to leaf, little figling. I'm no longer going to water you." and then getting pissed at it for dying as I was joking about above. This sounds funny, but it occurs with dogs when their behaviors die at an alarming level.</span></p>
<p><span>There are commonalities to all living organisms on this planet. We are all built to behave, we are all shaped by our reinforcement history (what works), and we all spend our behavioral energy where we can gain the most reinforcement. Behaviors that are tried and don't work go away. Behaviors that are tried and do work stick around. Learning is essentially gaining an understanding of what works and what doesn't.</span></p>
<p><span>Those plants of mine are subject to learn behaviors all the time. They've learned that if they turn their leaves toward the window, they optimize light intake, for instance.</span><br><span></span></p>
<p><span>I've been shaped by them. When I slack off they get wilty, I in turn perform the behavior of giving water to them, and in turn I am reinforced by their becoming lush again.</span><br><span></span></p>
<p><span>Susan J. Friedman, Ph.D. said behaviors are more accurately described as varying shades of strong. What she is describing is that no learned behavior is rigid in its form, it is forever influenced and flexible within its environment. High level, if coming when called has always yielded the best possibility of reinforcement for your dog, the behavior will be repeated time and again. If coming when called stops being reinforcing, or something out there in the world has consistently proved to be more reinforcing, they won't. Notice, it's all about what has happened in the past. </span></p>
<p><strong>The history of reinforcement.</strong><br><span></span></p>
<p><span>Here's the hard part, the Come to Jesus talk: We humans are really awful at accounting for our own failings in the responsibility department of our dog's behavior. As the keepers and doler outers of reinforcement, the blame for failed behavior is our burden to carry. Your dog might think, "If your reinforcement is shit, I quit!" So next time your dog fails to sit on cue, think to yourself, "This behavior is wilting. I need to provide it nourishment or it will die."</span><br><span></span></p>
<p class="medium-up--one-half" style="margin: 0 auto;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/103854336_10158502252285421_7825456394928580360_o.jpg?v=1593543572"></p>
<p><span>If you say things like, "He knows this! He's just being obstinate!" It sounds about as foolish as me getting mad at my plants for dying if I fail to care for them.</span><br><span>And if you've got your eye on a dog who is like a fig tree in a Colorado climate, know that it can work, but you as the tender of the garden are going to have to work extra hard to make it so.</span><br><br><span>Pictured: Behold my beloved new and old fig trees -- the latter loved so much I had my picture taken with it! </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/recipe-for-a-lemon-dog</id>
    <published>2020-06-22T11:44:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-22T11:44:23-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/recipe-for-a-lemon-dog"/>
    <title>Recipe for a &quot;Lemon&quot; Dog</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I love lemon. I love it so much my boyfriend groans because when asked what I want for dinner my go to is always, and I mean ALWAYS Piccata. I love lemon bars, lemon meringue, lemon cake, lemon zest, lemon in my tea.... But there's one place I've never liked to see lemons, and that's in dogs. While not for my taste, I am an expert on dogs and a fancier of lemons, so I'm taking one for the team here.</span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Now, I hate those recipe blogs who make you weed through the back story of a recipe, so for you cut-to-the-chase types, here you go. Cut it out and stick it on your fridge! </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s2"><b>Instructions: </b></span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><i>Fortunately, us owners don't have to do all the leg-work on this front. Factors prior to coming home can heavily impact your chances of creating a lemon dog. </i></span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><b>Step 1:</b> For strongest flavor, I recommend picking your puppy knowing full well one or both of the parents are unstable in one way or another. It may not always be possible to see the product first, so you can sub out for doggy parents you've never met before. Think pet stores, online ads, or breeders who give a million reasons why you can't meet there parents etc. Often these dogs are from "oops litters" or better, puppy mills. These large scale commercial breeding operations squeak by meeting bare minimum standards for the dogs they house. Puppy Mill dogs are the cream of the crop when creating a lemon dog.  Here are the bare minimums for my state of Colorado. Dreamy! </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><b>Step 2: </b>Be sure that the mother has had a stressful pregnancy. See recommended sources above. This is because stress in  utero is well known to cause behavioral issues and ain't no momma dog spending her pregnancy in a crate with grated floors surrounded by other stressed and pregnant dogs relaxed, amirite?! </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><b>Step 3:</b> Be sure to keep your puppy inside your house until they've had their final vaccination. Simmer that lemon-ey behavioral stew throughout their socialization window. This ensures they acquire no social skills and only see the real world once that developmental period has passed. It's like those kids who are locked in a closet for their childhood, only finally being discovered long after their developmental milestones are in the rear view. Sure, they may be able to learn a word or two, but man are they stunted emotionally and behaviorally. Except now in dog form.  </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Follow these steps, or even part of them! Play around with the recipe! You'll find that creating a lemon of a dog is actually quite easy. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/lemon-dog.jpg?v=1592847824" alt="Recipe for a Lemon Dog - Rocky Mountain Dog Training"></span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">In all seriousness, we know that creating a lemon of a dog is never anybody's goal. Our careers are dedicated to preventing this and to undoing it when it occurs. </span></p>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li4">
<span class="s3"></span><span class="s4">Sometimes the internet has steered us wrong. </span>
</li>
<li class="li4">
<span class="s3"></span><span class="s4">Sometimes well-meaning families pick up outdated books or watch outdated information on the TV and things go wrong. And by the way, I'm not immune to it either. I wasn't always a trainer and I've made plenty of mistakes and will likely make more in my lifetime with my dogs. </span>
</li>
<li class="li4">
<span class="s3"></span><span class="s4">Science is ever-changing. It's easy to fall behind, but don't be discouraged. That change means progress. That progress means better relationships in the long run with these lovely animals. </span>
</li>
<li class="li4">
<span class="s3"></span><span class="s4">Our fear of communicable disease gets the best of us.  </span>
</li>
<li class="li4">
<span class="s3"></span><span class="s4">Sometimes we get a puppy of unknown origin and we're working against the clock to make up but for real or possible deficits. There are a million reasons why dogs develop behavioral issues. Heck, sometimes we do everything right and we still see problems arise. </span>
</li>
</ul>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">My point is, there is so much research now that enables us to tip the behavioral scales heavily in our favor. We know very well what to do and very well what creates problems. We want to avoid creating problems. The above recipe is truly a recipe for disaster. I don't recommend it and yet it's still commonplace for puppies to have the deck stacked against them from the outset. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">It doesn't have to be that way. It shouldn't be that way.  Puppies are a huge undertaking that starts prior to coming home with you at the breeder. A good breeder will be selecting for quality genetics, not just in body but also in mind. They work hard to keep their mama dogs comfortable and low stress throughout pregnancy and will also work their butts off to provide early socialization to those puppies under their charge until they go home with you. Puppy Culture, Early Neurological Stimulation (ENS), and Avidog are all programs designed for breeders to start puppies off right and that's important! A huge chunk of their socialization window occurs before a puppy comes home. Nowadays some really great rescue groups also implement these procedures on puppies they take in or are born with them because they understand the importance. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Once your puppy is with you, you have to leave your house to get your puppy comfortable in the world and while we don't know exactly when the socialization phase begins to taper (likely because it varies from dog to dog), we do know it becomes harder for them around 12 weeks of age and exponentially more difficult or in some cases impossible after 16 weeks of age to get them well-socialized and habituated to the world at which point we're instead looking at behavior modification.  The point being, the earlier, the more thorough your efforts the better for puppy socialization. You can do this on your own or you can attend <a href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/products/puppy-socialization"><span class="s5">trainer-moderated socialization groups</span></a>. For busy families of which there are many, Our <a href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/pages/puppy-day-school"><span class="s5">Puppy Day School</span></a> is a great option where we do it all for you while you're at work and you still get that bonding time with your dog when you're home. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Whatever your route, just always remember, fear is the enemy in socialization and you need to vet your trainer carefully to be sure it's not just a free-for-all. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Prioritize socialization above all else. You can absolutely take training classes, teach your puppy skills along the way, but if you're short on time, puppy socialization is top priority because guess what? Your puppy is short on time too. You don't get that chance again. Training can happen at any age, socialization only for a short period in early development. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Last, I'm always a fan of adopting an adult dog. For the most part, what you see is what you get after a couple years of age. Behaviors of course can always crop up as pain and environmental factors and experiences are always going to factor. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s6"><a href="http://www.rockymountaindogtraining.com">Check out our website</a></span><span class="s1"> for more information on our puppy services. </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/private-training-why-are-you-so-expensive</id>
    <published>2019-12-10T15:22:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-22T11:25:11-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/private-training-why-are-you-so-expensive"/>
    <title>Private Training: Why Are You So Expensive?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h4>Why are private dog training sessions so expensive? You might be surprised to learn that it's all really expensive for us trainers too!</h4>
<p>I think this question comes up because on the surface, only the hour of time spent with the client is considered, and it's hard to grasp the behind the scenes expense of it, so in an exercise in transparency, I thought it might be helpful to dissect it a bit. After, I'll provide tips on how to keep costs as minimal as possible.</p>
<p>Private training is most often utilized for behavioral cases or specialized training. Behavioral cases are inherently more risky, and as a result, require extreme levels of focus and attention to detail and a specialized education to treat effectively.</p>
<p>While the type of protocol used doesn't vary much, customization comes into play based on the dog's current skills set, the handler's training goals and abilities, and then any environmental constraints that need worked around. This takes time and most often training plans are created back at the office factoring these pieces and prior to or following the actual consult. The trainer is still working for you outside of the session.</p>
<ul>
<li>Trainers carry various business insurance policies to protect you and protect themselves when working these cases. Expense goes up with higher liability risk cases.</li>
<li>Trainers have CPAs, Bookkeepers and sometimes attorneys advising them in their collective specialties and those expenses need to be factored.</li>
<li>Trainers have materials and education expenses.</li>
<li>Trainers often have to pay for their own private medical insurance. Taking behavioral cases without this could easily bankrupt us if we're out of work for an injury and no insurance to cover our treatment.</li>
<li>TAXES!!!</li>
<li>Trainers have websites, website admin fees, or alternately use and have scheduling software expenses. If they don't, they still need to factor their time it takes to keep everything current and running.</li>
<li>Trainers generally cannot take more than 3-5 private cases in a day, and as a general rule, the more complex the case, the less of a load can be taken on as time spent outside the session working the case increases as does the mental taxation these cases demand.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/SoExpensive_Final.jpg?v=1592845599" alt="Why private dog training is an expensive, but worthy investment - Rocky Mountain Dog Training"></p>
<p>After all of this, trainers still need to make a living wage if they're to stay in the field. It's a tough road, no kidding, but it needs to stay sustainable.</p>
<p>Good trainers are hard to come by because it's such a huge balancing act. It's a fine line between making a living and burning out. Take too much on and you're toast. Mentally and emotionally, you'll fry. Take too little on, and you can't survive. Cut corners and bad things happen.</p>
<h4>So let's talk about the best way to keep costs as low as possible as a consumer:</h4>
<p>Prevention, prevention PREVENTION!! Group classes and early socialization are very affordable and go a long way to decreasing a need for private training. We're pooling expense between all participants which lightens the load and groups are standardized so we can do more of them and help more dogs.</p>
<p>If purchasing a dog, good genetics and early puppy experiences and efforts at the breeder or rescue will also tip the scales in your favor. Vet your trainers well. Do they have an education or certifications? Are they following best and current humane practices in the field? You can burn through money like crazy with incompetent bargain trainers with nothing to show for it or worse, more damage to your dog because frankly, they don't always know what they're doing. They're actually practicing trial and error on your beloved dog. With the wrong trainer, and quoting my mentor, "You'll end up in the I Tried It And It Didn't Work Club."</p>
<p>Price is often (but not always) a good reflection of experience. Trainers who have been at it for a long while will charge appropriately. They know they can't live on $50 a session and cover all their expenses. They know the risks of burnout, they've made it out the other side and prioritize self care so they can stay in the game for the long haul. A trainer who is overly frazzled is ineffective and sometimes dangerous. Would you want a trainer who couldn't be fully present working with your bite-risk dog?</p>
<p>You can also decrease expense by following your trainer's instructions as designed. The more closely you follow these guidelines, the more efficiently you'll navigate the plan and get to resolution. If the trainer asks you to invest in high value treats, chews, interactive toys, muzzles, baby gates etc. they're not just trying get you to spend more money, they're trying to get you relief as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>Also, going rogue between sessions makes it really hard for us to help you and will often add expense. We have no idea what you're doing if you stray from the plan so having to dissect your activities second hand and then get back on track takes away time we could be working on next steps. Good trainers will follow a well-vetted plan, so that trainer will likely need to have you go back and do the steps she assigned at the last session, effectively making progress the previous week a wash.</p>
<p>We dog trainers are doing our very best to get you results as efficiently as possible. We're highly in tuned with the fact that if money runs out, or we crash and burn, families and dogs suffer.</p>
<p>I hope that helps to put your mind more at ease in your investment and gives you some useful insight into how to actually save in the long run.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/stay-in-your-lane</id>
    <published>2019-12-10T15:18:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-22T11:15:23-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/stay-in-your-lane"/>
    <title>Stay In Your Lane!</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h3>The hallmark of any good professional is knowing his/her limitations. </h3>
<p>I sometimes get asked about medical issues with dogs. <em>"Is this bump weird?" "Does it look like this dog is limping?" "What should I do?"</em></p>
<p>I can confirm, yes, <em>xyx</em> looks weird, but I immediately refer to a vet. I do this because I am not a vet, and I'm not trained in medicine, my schooling is in behavior. While we're talking about behavior, some behaviors need pharmacological support. Again, we as trainers may know of common meds used, but we don't advise on them because some meds interact with others with disastrous effect. This isn't our place. A vet will consider your dog's overall health, other meds they may be on and how they'll interact, etc. before treating. This isn't our wheelhouse. An ethical trainer will stay in their lane. The behavior lane.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/StayInLane_final.png?v=1592846071" alt="How to find a good dog trainer - Rocky Mountain Dog Training"></p>
<p>On the flip side, your vet may say, <em>"yes, this behavior is odd", </em>but should not then go on to dispense behavior advice. They are not trained in behavior, they are trained in medicine. They should refer you to a qualified, certified trainer. Unless your vet is a veterinary behaviorist who has been trained in both behavior and medicine (and there are only a couple in the state), it's unlikely they know the ins and outs of behavior modification, of puppy socialization and developmental milestones, or even operant conditioning (how we teach dogs new skills). They should stay in their lane. The medicine lane.</p>
<p>The hallmark of any good professional is knowing his/her limitations. While both fields are here to help, the greatest kindness to the animal is to get them to the right source via referral.</p>
<p>Recently, I've had clients who have been told by well intentioned but ill-informed vets all sorts of inaccurate information:</p>
<p><em>"Don't take your puppies out until they've had all vaccinations."</em> I get it. Diseases are scary, and their job is to keep a puppy free from illness.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, if you follow this advice, you will miss the most critical developmental window of this animal all together - the socialization period. This can be and often is disastrous for the dog and the household. You know what else is scary? Living with a dog who finds the world dangerous and has sharp teeth to keep themselves safe. And they're not wrong to find these things scary, they're just scared, and weren't properly socialized, or perhaps genetics are at play. Socialization tips the scales in our favor of having a well adjusted dog. Yes, some need more support in the long run, but it exponentially increases the likelihood of raising a behaviorally sound dog. Warehousing a puppy through their socialization period is a much higher risk than disease. And dogs die for it all the time.</p>
<p>I've had students under the misconception they need to "be alpha" or "show their dog who is boss" because their vet has advised them of this when a scared dog is barking at something that scares them. Just no. No, no, no, no, no. They aren't trying to rule the world, they're trying to stay safe. Behavior modification helps them to feel safe.</p>
<p>Please, when looking for behavioral expertise, go to the expert in behavior. And when looking for medical advice, go to the expert in medicine.</p>
<h3>When we all stay in our own lane, it's for the good of all involved.</h3>
<p>And if you're ever in need of an expert on both sides, let us know, we know some great veterinary behaviorists who can help.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dog-parks-why-i-love-them</id>
    <published>2019-12-10T15:18:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-22T11:25:10-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dog-parks-why-i-love-them"/>
    <title>Dog Parks: Why I Love Them</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>In our classes, I often get asked about dog parks. In the past, I've admittedly been on the fence about them, and at the root of it was my own lack of understanding that led to this stance. I was wrong. Nowadays, I am a huge supporter for the right dogs and <strong>let me explain why:</strong></p>
<p>Dogs are starved for the ability to interact with their own species. Often, the inability to play and practice species-normal behaviors can add to a dog's frustration when encountering other dogs. I also love them because they help busy people meet their dog's needs. We put in so many hours at work, it becomes challenging for us to do enough with our dogs and also get the down time we so desire and this creates a circular issue of a dog who needs and wants more, and who creates ways to meet their needs that we don't really love. This causes frustration in the relationship between us and them, frustration causes a lack of motivation to do anything, and guilt kicks in. The issue gets worse and worse.</p>
<p>Often, people will remark that dogs who go to the dog park get dog-crazed. Let's dissect that. Why do things become valuable? It's typically because they're rare. Why do we crave things? Because we haven't had access to them in a long while. With a dog who is social with other dogs, to deny their ability to engage with them makes them all the more valuable to the dog. When something is easy to access all the time, it loses its novelty. This is basic science.</p>
<p><strong>Let's talk science for a minute:</strong><br> Motivational Operations (MO) from a behavior perspective are tools that we can use to increase or decrease the value of something the animal finds reinforcing. Establishing Operations fall under the MO umbrella. For instance, if we want to make the food we're using MORE reinforcing, we would train when the dog is hungry. If a dog finds play with other dogs really reinforcing and we want to make it more valuable, we would deny access to play to make it a stronger reinforcer to dogs.</p>
<p>Abolishing Operations also fall under the MO umbrella. Abolishing operations (also known as saturation) can be used to make something that is highly motivating for the dog less motivating. We use this a lot in distraction training to decrease the value of the things competing with us for our dog's attention. Often distractions are really just rewards we can't control.</p>
<p><strong>Example:</strong><i> Let's say you looove pizza. Pizza is your #1 food of choice. That first bite is absolutely amazing, but by slice 3, pizza isn't as appealing to you. And if you sat down and ate a whole pizza and then someone brought you another, I'd guess that continuing to eat pizza is really no longer on your to-do list, at least for the time being.</i></p>
<p>This holds true for social dogs too. When I work with dogs in my level 2 distractions class, if they're really social with other dogs and struggle to focus in the class setting, right in their handouts we recommend they do some dog play 30 minutes prior to the training class (abolishing operations) and lo and behold: The dogs get saturated to play. SCIENCE! They get enough of it that when they get to training class, they're no longer hyper-focused on the other dogs in class. They can work beautifully with their owners. Our goal in class is focus on their people, and this is one way we get them there.</p>
<p>They've had enough play that engagement with their owners for food rewards is now the bigger draw for them. This is a purposeful step in helping dogs succeed at training in high distraction environments. It doesn't just need to be dogs, but you get the idea here.</p>
<p>Everything we do or don't do with dogs plays into a larger scheme of things. Denying dogs access to something they desperately want only serves to make that craving stronger. Granting lots of access to something they want serves to decrease its value. Science lesson over.</p>
<p>Now, back to dog parks. For pet dogs who love to socialize and play with their own species who live in busy households, this is such a fantastic option. Dogs can run and sniff and play and swim and come back to you more focused and ready to work, or chilled out so that the two of you can enjoy a relaxing evening together. And it happens fast! Most dogs don't need loads and loads of it to satiate their need.</p>
<p>For a very active dog, neighborhood walks just don't cut it and would take forever if you're looking to physically meet a dog's needs. But the dog park - it's quick and it's fun and it's got enrichment built in. Navigating social interactions and sniffing and digging and investigating it takes a lot of brain power. It's magical.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/dogparks_final.jpg?v=1592845928" alt="Why Dog Parks are Great - Rocky Mountain Dog Training"></p>
<h2>Best Practices:</h2>
<ul class="grid__item medium-up--one-half" style="padding: 30px; background: #fff; font-size: 13px; margin: 0 auto;">
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Dog parks aren't for all dogs. Your dog should enjoy play with other dogs.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">When you head to the park, your job is to supervise your dog because nobody else is going to. You don't let your dog be a bully and you don't let other dogs bully yours. Play bouncer for your dog. If they're trying to leave an interaction and they need an extra hand, you get in there and help them get space by body blocking the other dog. Really, if either dog is suspect of not enjoying it, intervene.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">If your dog is scared or uninterested in play, they're likely to prefer another activity (see my post about long line walks from a couple weeks ago).</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Even if your dog *was* playing great on arrival, if they start making poor choices they're probably tired. Take em home. There's always tomorrow. (Did you know when we do play at our facility, it's always around 30 minutes and there are activities mixed in to help the dogs get a break and to build other skills? Breaks are important!)</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Dogs who bully other dogs should be timed out for the behavior (they temporarily lose access to play), and if they continue, they leave for the day. This will look like a continuous targeting of one specific dog. It's inappropriate and unacceptable. Qualified trainers can help here!</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Some folks with really good intentions are misguided into thinking the dog park is a great place to teach their scared dog to not be scared. This is unfortunate but happens, and if you see it, steer clear of these dogs. They need space.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Dogs on leash at the dog park can get frustrated by not being able to access the other dogs, and this can look and sound scary, so give them space too.</li>
</ul>
<ul class="grid__item medium-up--one-half" style="padding: 30px; background: #fff; font-size: 13px; margin: 0 auto;">
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">If dogs are wearing metal or electric collars, avoid them. These can be risky for your dog to crack a tooth on or the other dog may associate any pain they feel with your dog and this is dangerous. Most dog parks post signs against using these tools in that setting. Personally I'd like them to go away forever, but that's for another day.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">If you're unsure if dogs are having a good time, ask them! Do a consent test. See links in comments.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Size the groups appropriately. Many dog parks have large and small dog areas and this is intentional. Use them. Size matters in play, and no matter how much your little guy likes play, we don't want to risk them getting stepped on and injured in it when big dogs are running.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Puppies should not be at dog parks. Disease risk for under-vaccinated puppies is very real. Choose a structured social group for them instead. There they will get padded with positive experiences so that later when they're older they can have a great time and have resilience to bounce back quickly if ever a negative experience occurs. If dog parks are in your pup's future, get them well-padded to play interactions in their socialization window so they're ready to roll in adulthood.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">Know that as dogs get older, sometimes their yearning for play decreases. Even if they loved play as a 1 year old, at 2 on if they're not as into it, it's okay. In fact, it's normal. Again, try a long line walk instead.</li>
<li style="padding-bottom: 10px;">A strong recall / coming when called behavior is a really good idea to have on board before hitting the park.</li>
</ul>
<p style="clear: both;"> </p>
<p>The deal with all environments for all species is that there are always risks, but we need to heavily evaluate the fairly low risk for high reward. I am sick to death of hearing about how insanely risky dog play is. The risk is minimal when you're responsible. You can always leave if needed. Dogs are by and large peaceful animals, and when they do actually squabble, yeah it's loud, but it's considered clean fighting in their world.</p>
<p>Anything beyond superficial scrapes are rare. Our fear of dogs because they communicate differently needs to be checked. Denying dogs the ability to be dogs is wrong. It's so narcissistic to think that we should be their only focus. It's not honoring the dog for the amazing animals they are. Yes, sometimes things can go wrong, but by and large they go right.</p>
<p><strong>A Word About Rare Event Reporting + Our Susceptibility To It:</strong><br> We often get hyper sensitive to risk because we are bombarded with horror stories all the time. They draw us in and hold our focus. It's more interesting for some reason. But of the hundreds of thousands of dogs that go to the dog park, most do so without incident. It's sad that "I took Luna to the dog park and she had a great time" isn't the more popular headline. Why are we so focused on the negative?</p>
<p>Please know that while dog parks aren't for all dogs, they are a great option for many, and can increase quality of life exponentially. If you know loads of dogs your dogs can play with in their own groups at home, you're so lucky, but that's not the reality for most pet dog people.</p>
<p>Let them Play!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dont-shake-the-baby</id>
    <published>2019-12-10T15:18:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-22T11:20:35-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/blogs/rmdt-dog-blog/dont-shake-the-baby"/>
    <title>Don&apos;t Shake the Baby!</title>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Parker</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Put Mealtime To Work For You When You Need Some Downtime.</strong></h3>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<p>It's universally understood in dog training circles that enrichment activities are a great quality of life increase for dogs. Scrap the food bowl, feed them out of toys. Meals that took them 30 seconds and left them looking for their next activity are turned into a brain game. A puzzle if you will. 20-30 minutes of activity using something they've gotta do anyway - eat.</p>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">In technical terms, you're simulating foraging activities, something that as scavengers by nature, dogs lov<span class="text_exposed_show">e.</span>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span class="text_exposed_show"></span></div>
<div class="text_exposed_show">
<p style="text-align: left;">But I'm gonna let you in on a little secret: It's not just about the dog. These toys are a gift from the heavens to you. Feeder toys = down time for stressed out puppy people. Relaxation, ahhh relaxation. Calgon, take me away...</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/dontshakebaby_final.png?v=1592845283" alt="Training and feed toys for your puppy - Rocky Mountain Dog Training"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Let's face it, dogs are hard work. They have a lot of needs and when those needs aren't met by us, they find ways to meet them themselves. As the species with the bigger brain, let's do our part and give them legal activities. When they're busy doing legal stuff it leaves little time to be doing illegal things.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">So here's my message to you, dear puppy people: Engage in self care. Invest in enrichment. When you're exhausted, but your puppy is just getting started, these toys are your solution.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: left;">And if your dog is a quitter (and some are), here are some tips:</h4>
<ul style="text-align: left;">
<li>Make it super easy to start. Add some primo treats to your mix.</li>
<li>If you're using something like wet food mixed with kibble in a stuffed toy, don't freeze it just yet. That'll come later.</li>
<li>If a <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #6aa84f;"><a href="https://amzn.to/2XpFrmc" title="Kong" style="color: #6aa84f; text-decoration: underline;">Kong</a></span> is too hard, try a <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #6aa84f;"><a href="https://amzn.to/2Fit0OR" target="_blank" title="Purchase a Toppl" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="color: #6aa84f; text-decoration: underline;">Toppl</a></span>.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2256/1033/files/Toppl_grande.jpg?v=1592846421" alt="Toppl Toy"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Get them addicted! Then, and only then, make it harder.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Welcome to the wonderful world of Don't Shake the Baby Toys!!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>|   For more ideas, head over to the <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #6aa84f;"><a href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/pages/suggested-shopping-list" title="Shopping List" style="color: #6aa84f; text-decoration: underline;">Enrichment &amp; Feeder</a></span> Toys section <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #6aa84f;"><a href="https://rockymountaindogtraining.com/pages/suggested-shopping-list" title="Shopping List" style="color: #6aa84f; text-decoration: underline;">here</a></span>.</strong></p>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
